RAJATH JAIPRAKASH

Summary

Site Reliability Engineer II with **3 years** of specialized experience in **Infrastructure Automation**, **CI/CD**, and **Logging/Monitoring pipelines**. Achieved over **50%** reduction in manual operations by designing and implementing **20+ Ansible** roles across production environments. Specialized in building Automation and proven contributor in cross team collaborations.

Skills

Programming: Python, Shell Scripting, C++, Powershell Scripting

Tools & Technologies: Ansible, Elasticsearch (ELK stack), Docker, GitHub Actions, Jenkins, Syslog-ng, Telegraf, In-

fluxDB, Grafana, Prometheus, NagiosXI, OpenSNMP, vSphere, ESXi, KVM **Currently Upskilling**: Kubernetes, OpenTelemetry, OpenNMS, Terraform

Certifications: The Linux Foundation: LFS162, Red Hat Certified Engineer (EX294)

Work Experience

Akamai Technologies | Site Reliability Engineer 2

Oct 2024 - Present

- Architected end-to-end **CI/CD pipelines** for our Access Border Routers by integrating it with our AAA Simulators and custom deployment scripts in collaboration with our QA team, making the process **4x** faster and reduced our downtime to just **30 seconds**.
- Engineered fault-tolerant system by developing **Python** based auto-remediation scripts for **8 critical services**, significantly reduced manual recovery procedures and improved service availability.
- Identified, Troubleshot and Solved a Business critical logging incident which impacted our 6WIND VSRs, across 18
 Distributed Edge sites.

Akamai Technologies | Site Reliability Engineer

July 2022 - Oct 2024

- Improved our deployment workflow by crafting **20+ Ansible** roles for automated configuration management, reducing deployment errors and cutting rollout time from days to hours across **4 environments**.
- Executed the complex migration of 18 production logging servers by designing comprehensive transition plan and implementing parallel cutover strategy, maintaining near 100% service availability and processing over 250K+ daily transactions without interruption.
- Revamped our logging infrastructure by optimizing, migrating and upgrading our ELK Cluster's to efficiently handle
 150 GB of daily logs each, resulting in a 300% increase in log search performance and enabling real-time anomaly detection for 20+ critical services.
- Spearheaded DevOps knowledge sharing initiative by conducting **6 technical workshops** for **30+ engineers** over **3 different time-zones**, resulting in **40%** fewer deployment-related incidents across development teams.
- Enhanced monitoring for **200+** nodes by implementing hierarchical alerting structure in **NagiosXI** using **InfluxDB** and **OpenSNMP Collector**, reducing false positives and redundant alerts by **70%**.

Projects

ClipForge - AI Driven Video Processing Pipeline

- Engineered an end-to-end local and open-source automated video generation pipeline by integrating **WhisperX**, **FFmpeg**, and **AI agents** created using **Langchain Python**. Project has received over 77k+ impressions to date.
- Built AI-based metadata generation, improving **SEO** and content discoverability by **40**%. Implemented automated **CI/CD** testing via **GitHub Actions**.
- Deployed on **Dockerized** Ubuntu containers with real-time **Discord** notification system, supporting 100+ daily video operations.

Education

PES University, Bangalore

2018 - 2022 GPA: 8.99/10

B.Tech in Electronics and Communication Engineering B.Tech Minors in Computer Science and Engineering